Inventory of the William Meade Papers 1807-1861
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence, 1851-1860., 29 items. (Box-folder 2:2-4)
  - Henry I. Whitehouse [Bishop of Illinois], Bloomington, Illinois, to [William] Meade, n.p., 30 April 1857., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Reports that one of the Virginia clergymen had moved into Whitehouse's district and that he had not reported to Bp. Whitehouse; asks Meade's advice.
  - W[illiam] Meade n.p., to the Reve[rends] John Grammar, John Black, William W. Pendleton, and Messeurs [sic] Blair Dabury and Edward Taylor n.p., [ca. June or July 1857]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Appoints these men as a court of inquiry in the case of the Rev. Mr. Castleman of Staunton, charged with trying "to persuade to sinful conduct" a female parishioner; notes that since the female has no witnesses, that her character must be carefully examined; urges them to fairly examine the charges and report their findings so that it can be determined whether a canonical trial be held.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to Rev. T. T. Castleman, n.p. 24 July 1857., 1 page. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Sends Castleman a letter dimmissory which he may present to the Bishop of Illinois; [Castleman had apparently earlier had ecclesiastical charges brought against him.]
  - W. R. Whittingham, Baltimore, [Maryland], to W[illia]m Meade, n.p., 25 July 1857., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Asks Meade for the testimonial required by canon for the transfer of a clergymen from one ecclesiastical district [Virginia] to another [Maryland].
  - W[illia]m Meade, Millwood, [Virginia], to Bishop [Henry I.] Whitehouse, [Illinois], 26 July [18]57., 1 page. Cy of LS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Transfer T. T. Castleman from the Virginia to the Illinois diocese; notes that he was acquitted of "improper familiarity with a female," but was suspended for six months for falsehoods relating to the same.
  - William Rollinson Whittingham, Baltimore [Maryland] to William Meade, n.p., 4 Aug[ust] 1857., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Informs him of the receipt of the satisfactory testimonial which Meade sent regarding the transfer of a Virginia cleric to Maryland.
  - W[illiam] M[eade], [1859]., 2 pages. AMsS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    [Endorsement reads], "Statement of Bishop Meade of something that occurred during the administration of communion at Gen. Convention in Richmond by which Bishop McCoskey was offended."
  - W[illia]m Meade, Alexandria, [Virginia], 26 April 1859., 2 pages. Cy of D[S]. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Expresses opinion on the election of vestrymen for St. Paul's Church in Alexandria; argues that since majority were present only for the election of 8 out of 12 vestrymen, that only those 8 should serve; the endorsement [in another hand] reads, "Opinion of Bishop as the lawfulness and expediency of ladies voting at the election of vestrymen." [This cannot be gathered from the letter, however].
  - W[illiam] Meade, Alexandria, [Virginia], to anon. minister, 11 May 1860., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Informs him that he cannot give him a dimmissory note; has asked three presbyters to examine his case and report the findings to Meade.
  - William Rollinson Whittingham, Baltimore, [Md.], to William Meade, Virginia, 8 September 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Notes that he is in receipt of Meade's notice of Rev. G. W. Mayer's six-month suspension; argues that if, as W understand, Mayer was privately and publicly reprimanded, denied a dismissory note, and advised to renounce the ministry all before he was tried, then Mayer was treated unjustly; Whittingham will receive him charitably on any dismissory note.
  Series 7: Correspondence, 1861-1870
- Correspondence, 1861-1870., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - W[illiam] Meade, Columbia, [South Carolina], to anon. correspondent, 29 Octo[ber] 1861., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Complains of bodily pains; reports the efforts of some in the newly-formed Southern Church to convince the convention to change the name to "Reformed Catholic;" North Carolina, Tennessee, and Mississippi bishops strongly advocated it, but it failed to pass, some wanted to denounce all other denominations, but to Meade's relief, that proposition failed; related the efforts of some to return to more "primitive church;" Virginia will be more alone in Southern Church [because of her more liberal views].
  - [William Meade], [Nov. 1861]., 4 pages. AMs. Fragment. (Box-folder 2:4)
    [According to endorsement], "Thoughts of Bishop Meade prepared for the Confederate Convention at Columbia [South Carolina the first Convention after the split of the Southern Church]; laments the factionalism among the Bishops; proposes reform in the Southern Church of the method of electing bishops; notes that the Bishops should not historically replace their own members; expresses desire of Virginia to "cast in their lot" with their Southern Brethren if it can be done without "the sacrifice of principle and right;" notes that the Virginia church is outnumbered by those who disagree with her; asks for charity.
  - [William Meade], [ca. 1861]., 2 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Discusses representation in various bodies throughout history: Israel, Greece, the Counsel of the Apostles in Acts, the German Confederation, Houses of Lords and Commons in England, American precedents. Asks what would be reaction in Confederate Congress [?] if such is the case with our church representation," he replies. [Apparently referring to the attempt of the Episcopal Churches which united in the South under the Confederation to give Virginia a lesser role in church matters.]
  Series 8: Correspondence, Undated
- Correspondence, n.d., 7 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - W[illiam] Meade, Norfolk, [Virginia], to Thomas Nelson, Richmond, Virginia, 29 March n.y., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Requests that he [Nelson] find a certain portrait painter who "took a picture of my wife some years ago" and who retained possession; asks him to send the picture down by the first boat.
  - W[illiam] Meade, Alexandria, [Virginia], D.C., to Mary Meade [sister], Shepherdstown, Virginia, 24 Aprill[sic] n.y., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Expresses concern that "Lucy" should be at Battletown before the Clerk of the County [at a certain time]; notes that Lucy must do this before leaving the state and that "Mr. Rochester" [?] "seems desirous to have her." [Apparently a slave]; relates personal news.
  - W[illiam] Meade, n.p., to Bishop [John] Johns, Richmond, Virginia, 29 Decem[ber] n.y, 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Notifies him that Mr. Macdoner [?] is on his way to his post; complains that his sermons are "too full of figures," and too long.
  - W[illiam] M[eade], n.d., 2 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Explains the practice of the primitive church in relations to clerical discipline; notes that the government of all the clergy and the exercise of discipline resided in the Bishop; noted that an appeal could be made to a synod of presbyters; reports that he has always asked the ecclesiatical court to express their opinion as to the punishment, since the Bishop might err.
  - [William Meade], n.d., 1 page. AMs. (Box-folder 2:5)
    [Endorsement reads], Notes of Bishop Meade on the sermon of Rev. R. H. Williams [?] before the Alumni. Refers to a conversation in which, interalia, the evils of Calvinism were objected to; reports that this minister [Williams] goes beyond the Church's teaching [apparently in condemning those who don't think as he does].
  - W[illiam] Meade, The Fork--Cumberland, [Virginia] to Philip Meade [son], Millwood, Virginia, n.d., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Mentions health, weather, and travel itinerary; advises him to get planks, "for enclosing a small bathing room under the stairs;" sends greetings and asks for health information.
  - W[illiam] Meade n.p., to Miss Susan Meade, Arlington, Virginia, n.d., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Expresses desire to visit; relates health and other personal matters.
  - [William Meade, ? (name scratched out)], to anonymous correspondent. n.d., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Explains that a publication written in his [?] youth and signed "Aurelius" now serves as a source of much sorrow and regret and he laments its present publication.
  Series 9: Correspondence - Addition
- Correspondence - Addition, 1 January 1851., 1 item. (Othertype Sm. Coll. Add. 20)
  - William Meade, Prospect Hill [Virginia] to Nathaniel Burwell, Baltimore, Maryland, 1 Jan[uary 18]51., 1 page. Cy of ALS. (Othertype Sm. Coll. Add. 20)
    Claims some booksellers may take a few of his journals but he does not trust Brunet [?], the Episcopal bookseller in Baltimore for he owes him money for books left with him and had told falsehoods about the money; Hanford & Iwards have sent 200 vols. to him [NB]; is sick with a cold; is writing in a hurry to give L. Paul time enough to get to Wichester [Winchester] tonight; all would send love if they knew he was writing.